Finding Aid for Gotthelf Carl Huber papers, 1874-1943
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Gotthelf Carl Huber papers 1874-1943
Huber, Gotthelf Carl, 1865-1934.
9 linear feet and 1 oversize folder
851536 Aa 2 UAm
Professor of anatomy and dean of the Graduate School at University of Michigan. Professional and personal correspondence largely relating to his activities in the medical school and graduate school; also diaries and University of Michigan student notebooks.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. G. Carl Huber (donor no. 33 ); additional material came from the University of Michigan Alumni Association (donor no. 1617 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Gotthelf Carl Huber was born in Hoobly, India, Aug. 30, 1865. He received his medical degree from the University of Michigan Department of Medicine and Surgery, Ann Arbor, in 1887, and later studied in Berlin and Prague. At the University of Michigan, Huber had served as assistant demonstrator of anatomy, instructor, assistant professor of histology, junior professor of anatomy and professor of histology and embryology and director of the histologic laboratory. In 1914, he became professor of anatomy and director of the anatomic laboratories. For many years he was also professor of histology and embryology at the University of Michigan Homeopathic Medical School and for one year, 1911 to 1912, he was professor of embryology at the Wistar Institute of Anatomy in Philadelphia. In 1927, he also became dean of the Graduate School.
Huber was a member, past president, secretary and treasurer of the American Association of Anatomists, and a member of the American Association of Pathologists and Bacteriologists and the American Philosophical Society. He was the official reporter of the section on anatomy at the seventeenth International Congress of Medicine in London and was chairman of the medical fellowship board of the National Research Council. For many years Dr. Huber was associate editor of the American Journal of Anatomy and managing editor of the Anatomical Record. He was the author of textbooks of histology and the editor of "Piersol's Human Anatomy." He died December 26, 1934.
The Huber collection consists of professional and personal correspondence largely relating to his activities in the medical school and graduate school. Most the letters written before 1900 are of a personal nature between Huber and his wife Lucy Parker Huber, including letters of her family. Worthy of mention are the letters Huber wrote while studying in Berlin, 1891-1892. Correspondence from later years is with professors and doctors in the United States and abroad and reflects Huber's professional interest in medicine and scholarly writings. Other materials in the collection are diaries, medical notebooks, and photographs. Huber's notebooks as a student are from classes taught by Edward S. Dunster, Alonzo B. Palmer, Volney M. Spalding, Joseph B. Steere, and Victor C. Vaughan.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Graduate School.; Medicine--Study and teaching--Michigan.; Physicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Anatomy.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Medical School--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Student notebooks.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Huber, Lucy Parker.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Huber family.; Huber, Gotthelf Carl, 1865-1934.; Parker family.; Parker, Lucy.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - 1884-1899, 36 folders (Box 1)
  - 1900-June 1911, 29 folders (Box 2)
  - July 1911-1916, 26 folders (Box 3)
  - 1917-July 1923, 32 folders (Box 4)
  - August 1923-March 1928, 30 folders (Box 5)
  - April 1928-1934, 33 folders (Box 6)
  - Family Correspondence, 1935-1937, 11 folders (Box 6)
  - Family Correspondence, 1938-1945 and undated, 14 folders (Box 7)
- Other materials
  - Miscellaneous subject files, 14 folders (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous medical notes (Box 8)
  - Diaries, 1894-1938 (Box 8)
  - Student notebooks (Box 8)
  - Photographs: portraits of Huber, family and friends; and other photos relating to Huber's life and career; and group portrait of Lucy Parker with Parker and Huber family members., See also oversize folder. (Box 8)
  - Student notebooks on courses taught by Edward S. Dunster, Alonzo B. Palmer, Volney M. Spalding, Joseph B. Steere, and Victor C. Vaughan (Box 9)